[Music]
y' think too small I got Big Dreams you
just starting them way ahead at the end
scenes started reading and dodging all
of the quick schemes money like your
[Music]
Spotify I Daniel and I'm Sarah and this
is the inquisitive podcast where we talk
about deals that don't make it all the
way to closing or struggle to close uh
we had to do some shuffling with
scheduling so this week Sarah and I are
talking about working capital and how
important it is to calculate working
capital in your deal a lot of my deals
are SBA 7A and um the bank is just like
don't worry about working capital we'll
get you over the express line of credit
and so we'll Lo it to you yeah and I you
know from my perspective as a third
party who not paying interest I'm like
sounds like you got it solved um
but recognizing that the interest rates
are pretty abysmal right now and um that
you could save a good deal of money by
just like altering the purchase price
account for some um liquidity on day one
um makes me think that's an area that I
could add more value to my clients that
was something that was missing from my
valuation tools because I I built out my
own valuation spreadsheets
interesting and yeah I was talking to a
really experienced business broker m&a
intermediary turned fractional CFO okay
and she was showing me hers and I show I
was going through mine and that's what
we do we you show me you show me yeah
you show me yours I'll show you mine
with Exel spreadsheets
no Between the Sheets yeah Between the
Sheets that's the spin-off
podcast where we where we share each
other's
spreadsheets gr there's so much more
there I'll
the
dorkiest anyway so um yeah so I I was
looking at uh you know net profit I was
looking at profit I was looking at the
p&l the balance sheet the tax returns
but she had this whole really beautiful
uh networking Capital breakdown that I
did I did not have and it's interesting
that you have that because I've been
suggesting that that's a really good
kind of what magnet is that what they
call it in marketing the first thing
that's free you get yeah lead there's
like a million it's a dime a dozen uh
how much is your business worth
calculators because every broker has one
of those um but there's uh not any like
how much working capital do you need
calculator and I know that that's not as
like click baity but um it'd be a lot
more useful uh because everybody it's
just everybody's really handwavy and I
think it's probably because it's you
know some some degree of just like
what's your comfort um and that's not
something you put in the Google Google
Sheets very easily yeah the advice came
from the logic that there's a chance
that a a liquidation was a better exit
than than actually selling like then
actually selling the business whole
interesting tell me about that yeah so
what she was doing with hers is she
would she would do like the typical sde
calculation so she she would take that
um take the a adbs to get the SD and
then do a multiple of SD then she would
also do a multiple of net
sales and then so that was like so those
were two different valuation models yeah
and then the third valuation model was a
liquidation so
basically uh what's your networking
capital what's your the value of your
equipment and then the value of like I
guess like your receivables minus
payables which is networking Capital so
like yeah so coming up with you know how
much could you feasibly walk away with
today if you just sold the the FFN and
collected on your receivables and called
it a day interesting yeah I guess there
were some cases where that made more
sense it was it was worth more to sell
it that way that's interesting well I
mean my dad had a construction company
uh growing up and that was what at least
his understanding which I never
questioned because I was a kid and he
was a dad running a business but the
theory was like that's what construction
company sell for is their FF is a lot
more
though in construction that's
substantial and then um you know
receivables cash in the bank um cash in
the bank is a big one there because you
have to get bonded um to do jobs so I
don't know um that's interesting I guess
it's a good de point to have because
really the what you're selling your
business for you think you're selling
your business for a million dollars but
if you could just walk away if you it's
the throw the keys in the Ravine you
know you throw the keys in the Ravine
you still walk away with like 300,000
then really the Delta is 700 so that's
how you should think about it well and
there's so many nuances to valuations
that I I feel like people just generally
don't know yeah I mean I only learned
what SD was when I started looking at
businesses that were for sale so yeah
it's just not it's not a number that you
really think about you know I only
recently at a a workshop a recasting
workshop found out that when you
calculate SD you're supposed to make
adjustments for a solo full-time owner
operator I know that that's true but I
don't know what adjustments you're
supposed to make what are you supposed
to make like you're supposed to build in
some kind of salary reasonable salary of
some sort but how is that established
yeah so the example that they gave was
uh husband and wife both owned a
business they both were full-time
operators so therefore the sde was one
of their full-time salaries as if they
worked 50 hours a week and then the
other was adjusted as an addback against
management expense okay but the logic
there made it was sound because the I
was looking at it from the sellers
perspective what is my benefit from the
business the logic behind SD is more of
like yes that's the seller's benefit but
what does the buyer need to anticipate
once they close yeah and if you have a
husband and wife even if they're work
both working full-time that's not to say
they're both required so you know that
the buyer could feasibly step in work 50
hours a week and do what's needed and if
they need that extra help then that that
spouse's salary would be allocated to
management not to
yeah yeah so I don't know but I think a
lot of people will look at um they'll
look at SD on Biz by cell and think like
this is what this is what's going to hit
my pocket after I buy this business yeah
that's true and that's not it's not true
that isn't what you're going to
necessarily get oh man um by the working
capital uh you know I was I had coffee
with a guy who um mentioned this and
then it's like repeated itself because
that's how way things go you know you
have like Trends and you'll run across
the same thing three times in a week
when you've not seen it in months but um
the theme of the week has been you know
deals where people maxed out the amount
that they could get in financing and
essentially forgot they need working
capital and then they're scrambling
super hard day one um like line you know
he lock on their house maxing out all
their credit cards to try to uh make
payroll which is um completely
foreseeable like you can I mean we can
see that all the way from here uh that
you are going to have a payroll cost
right after closing so to not build that
in at the front end is um just kind of
you know mismanagement of your deal so
in your opinion I know I know most deals
are cash free debt free but
should should you buy an operating
budget should the operating budget be
left in the bank account or
be transferred from seller to buyer so
that the business can continue to
operate seamlessly I don't know there's
some SBA requirements there that they
must disfavor having the cash uh change
hands the operating account um just
staying in there they want it to be like
pulled out and then I can't decide I
can't tell if it's that the bank is
wanting to sell their Express line of
credit product um and so they're just
like don't do that you know just use
more you know get more of our loans um
or if there's an SBA requirement I
haven't looked into it but um I just it
needs to be planned for so if you're
going to BU to you know the bank will
only loan you $1 million then you should
not pay $1 million for the company right
you should pay $1 million less what
working capital you need what has been a
reasonable amount of working capital in
the deals that you've structured I think
High higher level question super
variable I was looking at I actually
found the definition this is Black's Law
Dictionary and I was looking it up at
because you know I think it's funny to
to start every like online course um
kind of uh like you start a toast When
You're Made of Honor like Webster's
Dictionary defines love as that is how
you would start a wedding toast isn't it
yeah I mean you know my Made of Honor
days are behind me guess probably for
that reason you have to make sure
everyone's on the same
page yeah yeah exactly well just to be
clear we're talking about this kind of
love um yeah so we's see it doesn't
actually have working capital in Black's
Law so then you have to go all the way
to mergers and Acquisitions A to Z and
then flip way to the back for working
capital um which is like that makes
sense right because lawyers don't know
anything about business so why would
they have working capital in there
in answer to your actual question um the
amount of working capital that you need
after closing can vary super super super
widely and just to um identify it from
the most like basic example from you
know the standard that I always go to of
uh accounting practices because it's
pretty um standardizable there's some
folks get paid one time a year and they
get paid like right at tax season and so
there's this huge amount of accounts
receivable that hit in April May and
then there's absolutely nothing for the
remainder of the year and in that case
you need like you know 10 11 months
depending on when you buy the practice
um 10 11 months working capital which is
ridiculous and really arduous um I
recently had a deal that was exactly
that and they kept saying I they didn't
explain what they meant at first but
they kept saying um the accounts
receivable were very bumpy or yeah very
bumpy accounts receivable and I was like
what do you mean but they just meant
there's one big bump and that's it for
the
year um alternatively if you have a
bunch of monthly recurring Revenue you
know you need like 20 30 days of
overhead to cover yeah I mean I think
probably like regular people would think
what overhead and I think if you were
just trying to figure it out really
basically without a professional you
might pull the checking account
statements of the business and see all
of their actual expenses for the last
like you know on a monthly basis for the
last three months six months in a year
and then you know average it out that's
what I would do most businesses like I
feel like a business that gets paid once
or twice in an entire calendar year are
kind of outliers I I just don't think
that there's so many of those the the
vast majority are going to have uh
inflows of cash so yeah I typically
recommend two to three months worth of
operating
expenses and that could also include
wages although I tend to be a little bit
more conservative when it comes to
paying people and especially with things
like covid and recent memory so I like
to think you know maybe closer to six
months worth of payroll banked up I like
that true answer two to three months
worth of operating expenses like
idealistic scenario three months worth
of operating expenses and six months
worth of payroll I think that that would
make me feel more comfortable as well um
I another example that was really
crunchy um was ski company they have a
real season ability to them like they
get all their orders you know the vast
majority of their orders in the fall and
then like there's nothing in the summer
so I was looking at one of those
deals usually you're keeping people on
year round and they've got so you know
and you have office space and or you
know retail space um and Manufacturing
and all of that stuff still needs to
keep moving but it's very very like you
know it it very much depends like the
same buyer would need a radically
different amount of working capital
after closing based on when they closed
so that's confusing because as we know
deals never happen when they're like
anticipated so if it's going to go for
another month and another month and
another month then that's going to keep
like shift and if it's shifting by a
couple thousand dollars that's not a big
deal but if it's shifting by you know 50
100 Grand and that's a lot in the
context of the deal then that could um
make or break it yeah that accounting
firm that I was looking at we were
negotiating in
December uh like November early December
we were targeting a close a closing in
January February which would have put me
closing before tax season and it was a
very tax heavy firm so it was like a
zero working capital scenario it just
wasn't necessary because by the time we
actually closed and went through um like
the initial transition and like kind of
got the keys uh then we were going to
start receiving all that revenue from
tax season but as we went through the
back and forth with the LOI and the
closing date was getting moved out
further and further we started to get to
a point where it was like okay now it
doesn't make sense to close during tax
season so if we are going to do this
deal we need to push the whole thing by
four months and now I need working
capital because I'm going to miss out on
you know 90% of the annual revenue is
that practice still for sale it is off
Market but privately for sale I always
wondered um like was it just too much
ret Trading to or did you think about
going hey I just need to radically
retool this purchase price here to
account for everything it was way low on
the SD for what I really wanted I wanted
to buy a firm like I live in Vero Beach
but I'm within two hours of Orlando
Tampa Miami yeah so I really wanted a
firm that was going to be larger in one
of those places where it's easier to
recruit and easier to fly clients into
if we ever want to bring someone on site
yeah and you just have larger firms in
those areas it didn't make sense I think
it would be cool to have you know little
office building here in town and like
you know be able to do business here but
there was just no great way to scale
that I'll be back looking probably later
this year again and uh but minimum SD
probably
750,000 I don't think it makes sense to
go below that and you're going to be
looking in that 2hour Geographic scope
yeah I've got one there's one in my
Miami that I want so bad really how far
away is that two hours really what there
things are so close out east like it's
ridiculous I can't drive two hours to
anything in the I guess Midwest flyover
states I talked to the firm owner um a
while back they focus on U multinational
taxation which is huge when you're like
a digital Nomad or your professional
service provider when you work online
and you can work from anywhere
um there is a big incentive to go and
work in other countries yeah and Most
accountants just won't even touch it I
haven't been able to touch it and I've
never really been able to build a good
referral partnership with someone who
would and being in Miami they did get
their start with people who split their
time between Miami and South America but
now they have an entire division for
European expats and oh man you could
Market that digitally so well it'd be
ridiculous yeah and it's not really
marketed at all it's like all word of
mouth it's a beautiful firm it's like I
mean the by the numbers I mean the
firm's probably beautiful too I haven't
been there but the numbers are beautiful
um so yeah when he's ready to sell I'm
gonna jump all over that oh man that' be
great digital Nomad and there's got to
be so many like puns in there yeah
there's just not a there's not a ton
that focus on that or or have solutions
for that need well it feels like you
know in the same way that lawyers are
accountants kind of spring up with local
um needs and they just address everyone
who's in their Geographic areas needs
and inevitably one or two people will be
like I also have property in Mexico or
you know I split time between here and
um the Virgin Islands but you know it's
not in any of those local accountants
best interest to be like let me dig in
on this one weird specific issue for you
that's true we do we dealt with that a
ton the more we pushed into Texas
working with businesses in Texas it
seems like there's a good population a
good siiz population in Texas that will
also have some portion of their company
in Mexico or in like one guy had a a
whole division in Brazil it's easy to
travel from Texas to Mexico and South
America and harder the other way around
um so like I I hear you can just swim
from Mexico to Texas that's really
interesting because you'd be kind of uh
marketing B2B instead of B Toc because
it's really other accountants who don't
want to that liability or specialization
who would be such a good referral source
and that's and accountants are kind of
easy to Market too that's the hack right
it's yeah it's easy to figure out the
the owner of the business when the
business is there their name yeah you
can like go on LinkedIn and filter by
CPAs or EAS or anything else and just
they're all right there you don't even
have that with lawyers so it's kind of
nice well this has been episode 9 where
we've talked about working capital and
the most important part is don't forget
about it and check out deal academy.org
for a course to help you determine
exactly how much working capital you
need to factor in if you got some value
from this like And subscribe and tune in
next week I got make it for kids and for
kids kids that's weth years and years
promise my brother soon as he out to
finish this we to do it bigger than
anybody